

Zhengxu Yu Alibaba Cloud, Alibaba Group

→ +86-18685885459

✓ yuzxfred@gmail.com

Homepage: https://zhengxuyu.github.io DBLP: https://dblp.org/pid/246/3155.html

ORCIDo: 0000-0002-6059-0300

RESEARCH OVERVIEW

My research focuses on developing generative decision-making AIs capable of independently solving real-world problems, particularly temporal-spatial problems in urban scenarios. Two unique challenges arise in this context:

- 1. Lack of Decision-Making Data and Generalization: To address this, I build a Digital Twin simulator with generative models to generate training data for unseen scenarios.
- 2. **Model Transferability Across Tasks**: I propose generative decision-making models, including LLM-based RL models, that require minimal fine-tuning for task transferability.

My work demonstrates how the integration of simulators and decision-making models can solve various real-world urban problems, from multi-agent control to hierarchical planning. Currently, I am enhancing these models by integrating the planning and reasoning capabilities of Large Language Models (LLMs) with RLs for complex urban applications.

Research Interests: Machine Learning, Reinforcement Learning, Decision Making, Generative Models.

EDUCATION

•Ph.D. in Computer Science and Technology

2017/09-2021/03

Zhejiang University, China

Advisors: Prof. Deng Cai, Prof Xiaofei, He

Research Area: Reinforcement Learning, Graph Neural Networks, Stable Learning Thesis: Stable Learning for Non-I.I.D Data and its Application in Traffic Domain

•M.S.c in Information System

2015/09-2016/12

Surrey University, UK

Advisors: Prof. H Lilian Tang

Research Area: Convolutional Neural Networks, Deep Learning based Data Mining methods

Thesis: CNN-based Mycobacterium Cells Segmentation for Time-lapse Images

•B.S. in Communication Engineering

2011/09-2015/06

Jilin University, China

EXPERIENCE

•Alibaba Cloud, Alibaba Group Senior Algorithm Engineer Hangzhou, China 2023/10-present

- Leading the R&D team for the Decision Making Agent Project
- Developing Decision Making Models within urban scenarios
- Exploring the frontiers of reinforcement learning especially LLM-based RLs
- Supervising Engineers and Research Interns

•DAMO Academy, Alibaba Group Senior Algorithm Engineer Hangzhou, China 2021/04-2023/11

- Leading the R&D team for the Digital Twin Project
- Developing the Camera Perception and Simulation System of Digital Twin Project
- Exploring the frontiers of reinforcement learning, digital twin, and data mining
- Developing the Crowd Monitoring System
- Leading the Accident Risk Personnel Forecast Project
- Supervising Engineers and Research Interns

•DAMO Academy, Alibaba Group

Research Intern

Hangzhou, China 2018/01-2021/04

- Exploring the frontiers of reinforcement learning and graph neural networks
- Developing the Urban Traffic Prediction System
- Developing the Signal Control System

•Outstanding Intern Alibaba Group

•Outstanding Postgraduate Student Zhejiang University

2019-2020

PUBLICATIONS

- P1 Xiang, Chao, Zhongming Jin, **Zhengxu Yu**, Xian-Sheng Hua, Yao Hu, Wei Qian, Kaili Zhu, Deng Cai, and Xiaofei He. "Optimizing traffic efficiency via a reinforcement learning approach based on time allocation." International Journal of Machine Learning and Cybernetics 14, no. 10 (2023): 3381-3391.
- P2 Zhengxu Yu, Zhongming Jin, Long Wei, Jianqiang Huang, Deng Cai, Xiaofei He, Xian-Sheng Hua. "Progressive Transfer Learning." IEEE Trans. Image Processing (TIP), vol. 31, pp. 1340-1348, 2022, doi: 10.1109/TIP.2022.3141258.
- P3 Peng, Liang, Fei Liu, **Zhengxu Yu**, Senbo Yan, Dan Deng, Zheng Yang, Haifeng Liu, and Deng Cai. "Lidar point cloud guided monocular 3d object detection." ECCV 2022.
- P4 Xin Guo*, **Zhengxu Yu*** (*Co-first author), Pengfei Wang, Zhongming Jin, Jianqiang Huang, Deng Cai, Xiaofei He, and Xian-Sheng Hua. "Urban Traffic Light Control via Active Multi-agent Communication and Supply-Demand Modeling," in IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering (2021), doi: 10.1109/TKDE.2021.3130258.
- P5 **Zhengxu Yu***, Yilun Zhao* (*Co-first author), Bin Hong, Zhongming Jin, Jianqiang Huang, Deng Cai, Xian-Sheng Hua. "Apparel-invariant Feature Learning for Person Re-identification." IEEE Transactions on Multimedia, doi: 10.1109/TMM.2021.3119133.
- P6 Wang, Wenxiao, **Zhengxu Yu**, Cong Fu, Deng Cai, and Xiaofei He. "COP: customized correlation-based Filter level pruning method for deep CNN compression." Neurocomputing 464 (2021): 533-545.
- P7 Zhengxu Yu, Shuxian Liang, Long Wei, Zhongming Jin, Jianqiang Huang, Deng Cai, Xiaofei He, Xian-Sheng Hua. "MaCAR: Urban Traffic Light Control via Active Multi-agent Communication and Action Rectification." IJCAI-PRICAI'2020 (Acceptance Rate: 12.3% (592/4717)).
- P8 Liang Xie, Chao Xiang, **Zhengxu Yu**, Guodong Xu, Zheng Yang, Deng Cai, Xiaofei He. "PI-RCNN: An Efficient Multi-sensor 3D Object Detector with Point-based Attentive Cont-conv Fusion Module." AAAI'2020 (Acceptance rate: 16.2% (1150/7095)).
- P9 Long Wei, Zhenyong Wei, Zhongming Jin, **Zhengxu Yu**, Jianqiang Huang, Deng Cai, Xiaofei He, Xian-Sheng Hua. "SIF: Self-Inspirited Feature Learning for Person Re-Identification." IEEE Trans. Image Processing (TIP) 29: 4942-4951 (2020).
- P10 **Zhengxu Yu**, Zhongming Jin, Long Wei, Jishun Guo, Jianqiang Huang, Deng Cai, Xiaofei He, Xian-Sheng Hua. "Progressive Transfer Learning for Person Re-identification." IJCAI'2019 (Acceptance rate: 17.9% (850/4752)).
- P11 Long Wei*, **Zhengxu Yu*** (*Co-first author), Zhongming Jin, Liang Xie, Jianqiang Huang, Deng Cai, Xiaofei He, Xian-Sheng Hua. "Dual Graph for Traffic Forecasting." IEEE ACCESS (2019).
- P12 **Zhengxu Yu**, Pengfei Wang, Junkai Xu, Liang Xie, Zhongming Jin, Jianqiang Huang, Xiaofei He, Deng Cai, Xian-Sheng Hua. "Stable Learning via Causality-based Feature Rectification." arXiv preprint arXiv:2007.15241.